To deal with nonlinear functions, the UKF uses the unscented transformation.
要处理非线性函数 UKF 使用无损转换
Let's quickly summarize again what the problem is with
我们再快速总结一下
nonlinear process models or nonlinear measurement models.
非线性过程模型或非线性测量模型的问题所在
Let's start again from the point where we have the state vector mean x and
假设我们有状态向量均值 x
the state covariance P a time step k.
和状态协方差 P 以及时间步 k
What we want to do is predict the mean and the covariance to time step k+1.
我们要做的 是预测到时间步骤 k+1 的均值和协方差
So we have X k + 1 pipe k, and P k + 1 pipe k.
我们有 Xk+1|k 以及 Pk+1|k
You haven't seen this notation system yet.
你还没见过这个命名系统
I want to introduce it here because it is often used in the literature or
在这里介绍一下 因为它在文献或维基百科上
on Wikipedia.
经常用
k pipe k means the estimation is for time step k, and
k|k 表示估算是时间步 k 的 而且
the measurement at time k has already been taken into account.
时间 k 的测量值已经考虑在内了
The is also called the posterior estimation.
这也叫做后验估算
k +1 pipe k means the estimation is for time k+1 but
k+1|k 表示估算是时间步 k+1 的 但是
the last measurement that has been taken into account was from k.
最后一个考虑在内的测量值是来自 k 的
This is exactly what we have after the prediction.
这就是预测后的结果
And this is also called the a priori estimation.
这也叫做先验估算
Now, what do these ellipses mean?
现在 这些椭圆是什么意思？
They visualize the distribution of our uncertainty.
它们描述了我们的不确定性分布
All points on this line have the same probability density.
这条线上的所有点都有着同样的概率密度
If the uncertainty is normally distributed,
如果不确定性是正态分布的
these points have the shape of a ellipse.
这些点就呈椭圆形排列
It is often called error ellipse.
它经常被叫做误差椭圆
It can be seen as the visualization of the covariance matrix P.
可以看作协方差矩阵 P 的可视化
If the process model is linear, the prediction problem looks like this.
如果过程模型是线性的 则预测问题看起来是这样的
Here, Q is the covariance matrix of the process noise.
这里 Q 是过程噪音的协方差矩阵
We can use the Kalman filter to solve this linear prediction problem.
我们可以使用卡尔曼滤波器求解这个线性预测问题
How does this case look like if the process model is nonlinear?
如果过程模型是非线性的 这种情况看起来是怎样的呢
Then the prediction is defined by a nonlinear function, f,
如果这样 预测就通过非线性函数 f 定义
as we've just derived it for the CTRV remodel.
我们刚刚根据 CTRV 模型推演过
Predicting with a nonlinear function provides a distribution which is
使用非线性函数预测提供了一个分布
generally not normally distributed any more.
一个通常不再正态的分布
Actually it's not so easy to calculate this predicted distribution.
实际上 计算这个预测分布没那么容易
Generally, it can only be calculated numerically.
一般来说 只能通过数字计算
Let's say we use some fancy algorithm which can do that, and
比如 我们有中很好的算法能算出来
let it run for a while.
并且运行了一段时间
Then result might look like this.
结果可能看起来是这样的
By the way, later in the localization course you will implement an algorithm
顺便说一下 在后面的定位课程中 你需要实现一个算法
that does this kind of numerical calculation.
来进行这种数字运算
It's called a particle filter.
叫做粒子滤波器
As you can see, this is not a normal distribution any more.
你能看到 这不再是正态分布了
Otherwise, it would be an ellipse again.
否则 这里还会是椭圆形
So the predicted state distribution is not normally distributed any more.
因此 预测的状态分布不再和平常一样 呈正态分布了
But what the UKF does is keep going
但是 UKF 所做的 是继续
as if the prediction was still normally distributed.
好像预测仍然正态分布一样
This is not an analytical path any more.
这不再是一条分析路径了
Of course, it is an approximation.
当然 它是一个近似
What we want to find now is the normal distribution
我们现在想确定的是 尽可能
that represents the real predicted distribution as close as possible.
贴近真实预测分布的整体分布
So what we are looking for is the normal distribution that has the same mean
也就是说 我们寻找的是和这是预测分布的
value and the same covariance matrix as the real predicted distribution.
平均值和协方差矩阵一样的正态分布
And this mean value and the covariance matrix might look like this.
平均值和协方差矩阵能是这样的
The question is, how do we find this mean vector and this covariance matrix?
问题在于 如何才能找到这个均值向量和这个协方差矩阵？
And this is what the unscented transformation does for
这时候 我们就要用到无损转换了
us, as I will show you in the next video.
我们下次视频讲